I attended my high school reunion
我上个礼拜
last week.
高中同学聚会
There was a girl
然后有一个姑娘
carrying a luxury bag.
背了一个名牌包
But when she was in high school,
她上高中的时候
she applied for an exemption
可是向学校
from the school.
申请了免学金的
We now suspect that she
我们现在都怀疑她
lied about her family.
谎报家情
Ran Da's family must be poor.
冉达家当然穷了
I was in the same high school as him.
我当时跟他一个高中
I know it very well.
我太了解了
His dad was laid off and his mom left early.
他爸下岗 他妈早退
At that time,
他那个时候
in order to save two yuan on bus,
为了省两块钱公交车钱
he rode three hours
天天骑车
to and from school every day.
三个小时上下学
Even if his application is true,
就算他的申请表是真的
he has money
他都有那个闲钱
to buy roller skates,
去买轮滑鞋
which means that he is not in trouble enough
就说明他还没有困难到
to need a subsidy.
拿补助
What exactly is considered poor?
那到底多穷才算穷啊
Do we need to hold
是不是还得开一个
a tragedy competition?
比惨大会
In order to pay back
我为了还静雯
the 1,500 yuan that Jingwen lent me,
借我的一千五百块钱
I can only
这个月只能
eat your meals this month.
吃你们几个的了
Am I miserable?
我算不算惨
Can I apply for it?
我能不能申请一下
So the review team
所以为什么要
is set up
设置评议组
to eliminate people like you.
就是为了杜绝你这种人
Before, a senior
之前有个大四的学长
took time off to go back to his hometown
他每年固定时间
at a fixed time every year.
都会请假回趟老家
He said that because his parents were in poor health,
说是家里父母身体不好
he would go home to help collect corn.
要回家帮忙收玉米
At first, we all thought he
一开始我们都以为他
was joking.
在开玩笑
We didn't know it was true
直到后来
until he
他每次开学的时候
brought several boxes of corn
回来都会成箱成箱地
to us every time
带玉米送我们
he came back from home.
我们才知道是真的
I had dinner with that high school classmate
就我那个高中同学
last semester.
上个学期跟她吃饭
She told me
她跟我说
that she kept every meal
她顿顿都控制在
within three yuan.
三块钱以内
She just ordered a vegetarian dish
就点一个素菜
and a steamed twisted roll.
和一个花卷
Later, the price increased.
后来学校涨价了
She only changed the steamed twisted roll into the steamed bun.
只能把花卷换成馒头了
Do you understand?
你们看到没有
This kind of student
就是这种学生
will never buy
就算拿到了补助
a luxury bag
也绝对不会去
even if she gets subsidies.
买名牌包的
Where does
你那个朋友
your friend get the bag?
包是哪儿来的
I don't think
我就觉得吧
this is logical at all.
一点都不合逻辑
He has his own roller skates.
人本身就有轮滑鞋
He doesn't buy roller skates
人是拿这笔钱
with the money.
去买轮滑鞋的吗
They are completely different.
完全两码事啊
What if
这万一
this is what he got in the lottery?
是人家抽奖抽到的呢
this is from the parents
救一落水儿童
after he saved a drowning child?
人爹妈送的呢
What if he picked this up in the street?
万一人大街上捡的呢
She tells me
问到了
that this bag is
是她男朋友
from her boyfriend.
为她买这个包
He works two jobs.
自己打两份工
He is so tired that he catches a high fever,
累到发高烧
but he doesn't go to the hospital.
都不舍得去看病
Could it be that
会不会
they saved money together to buy it?
是两个人一起存钱买的
Because the boy loves the girl dearly,
男方心疼女方
he pays more.
所以多付出了一些
Maybe.
也是
If it comes from a special channel,
如果是特殊渠道来的
it seems a bit cruel
咱们就这么剥夺人家
for us to deprive her of
偶然的这个奢侈的权利
this accidental luxury right.
好像是有点残忍哦
Let's have a look tomorrow.
明天再去看看吧
Give me a hand with the cards.
你帮我发一下
I play cards with Dandan,
和蛋蛋玩
and my forehead is swollen.
弹脑门被弹肿了
The third sign of liking someone
喜欢一个人的表现三
is that you can't help
总是忍不住地
chatting with him
想要和他聊天
and giggle with your mobile phone.
并且会抱着手机傻笑
Lin Dingxiang, Zhou Xiaoyu.
林丁香 周小雨
Ran Da.
冉达
I don't know if Nan Bei
也不知道南北和小鱼
has reached an agreement with Xiaoyu.
达成共识没有
You don't grasp
你根本没有把握
the essence of this matter at all.
这件事情的本质
But I think
但我觉得
he can get the subsidy
只要这鞋
as long as he didn't
不是他自己买的
buy the shoes himself.
他就可以领补助啊
I'm not talking about this.
我说的不是这件事情
He also meets this standard
那他其他方面
in other aspects.
也都符合这个标准
I'm talking about Xiaoyu and Nan Bei.
我说的是小鱼跟南北
Think about it.
你看啊
Nan Bei usually
南北平时
does Xiaoyu's bidding, right?
对小鱼唯命是从的吧
But why
但是为什么在
does he go against Xiaoyu
这个节骨眼上
at this critical moment?
要和小鱼对着干呢
Of course.
当然了
It's a fact that they have different opinions.
他俩意见相左是事实
But don't you think
但是你不觉得
Nan Bei is a bit arrogant this time?
南北这次有点刚吗
Yes, a bit.
是有一点
That means
这就说明啊
they're going to be together soon.
他俩好事将近了
Really?
真的吗
That's strange.
不对呀
If so, Nan Bei should
那这样南北不是应该
be more obedient to Xiaoyu.
更顺着小鱼吗
It looks like
他们看上去
they're discussing about Ran Da.
是在讨论冉达的问题
In reality,
实际上
they're arguing about the dominance of marriage.
是在争论婚姻的主导权
How is that possible?
怎么可能
You think too much.
你想太多了
If you don't believe me, just see the result.
那你不信你等着看好了
Trust me.
信我准没错
You think this matter too complicatedly.
你想太复杂了
You think this matter too simply.
是你想得太简单了
I don't.
我哪简单了
Why
不是
do we argue about this?
我们俩争论这个干嘛呀
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Why are you so weird?
你怎么奇奇怪怪的
You stand there and don't move.
你站那儿别动
If you have anything to say,
你有什么话
just stand there and say it.
站那儿说得了
I wanna tell you
我是想跟你说
about Ran Da.
冉达的事情
Dandan investigated
蛋蛋去调查了一下
the origin of his shoes.
他那个鞋是怎么来的
He said he had news.
说有消息了
Let's go together.
走 一块去呗
You...
你 你
Why should I go with you?
我干嘛要跟你一块去
What?
怎么跟我干嘛
Let's go.
走了 走了 走
Don't touch me.
你不要拉拉扯扯的
You...
你
All right, let's go together.
一块去就一块去
You go ahead.
你走前面
What's the matter?
干嘛
I'll keep a distance of two meters from you.
我要跟你保持两米距离
You go.
你走啊
Don't look back.
你不要回头看
Right.
对
Dandan
蛋蛋
Do it again.
再来一次 走
You just practice by yourself.
你先自己练啊
Take your time.
慢慢练
OK.
嗯好 学长
You're weak.
不会办事
All the contents on Ran Da's application form
冉达申请表上的
are true, right?
内容全都属实吧
Absolutely.
绝对属实啊
That's good.
那好了
If you continue
如果你还像以前一样
to vote against it as before,
一直投反对票的话
you must first prove
那你就一定得先证明
that excessive consumption
有过高消费
must mean that the family is not poor
就一定代表家庭不困难
or not poor enough.
或者是不够困难
I've figured this out.
这点我已经想通了
I can't prove it.
我没有办法证明
So now I just need to know
所以现在我只要了解
that as long as he can prove
只要他能够证明
that he has special channels
他有特殊渠道
and this pair of shoes was not bought by him,
这双鞋不是他买的
I believe
那我就认定
that he is eligible for subsidy.
他有补助资格
He bought it himself.
就是他自己买的
So I still disagree.
那我还是不同意
Don't jump to conclusions,
你别那么着急下结论
okay?
好不好啊
It's different
用一个月的零花钱买的
to buy it with one month's pocket money
和攒了
and with one semester's pocket money,
一个学期的零花钱买的
okay?
这不一样好不好
He bought it after working for two months
是他暑假
in summer vacation.
打两个月工买的
Look.
你看吧
I feel sorry for him
我跟你们一样
as much as you do.
我也很同情他
I'm just against him in this matter.
我只是反对他这件事情
Why?
为什么
Because the fact that he earns so much money
因为他打工
from his part-time job
能挣这么多钱
proves that he doesn't really need
就证明他并不是很需要
the grant.
这笔助学金
There must be someone who needs it more.
一定有更需要的人
I find you
我发现你就是
too narrow-minded.
想法太狭隘
You...
你
Got in trouble, right?
惹事了吧
You finish the work?
你忙完了
Yes.
嗯
And you?
你呢
I need a little more time.
我再忙一会儿
Do you still remember
你还记不记得
that you promised me
你之前答应过我
that you would accompany me
说只要我有了
wherever I wanted to go
属于我自己的时间
as long as
我想去哪儿
I had my own time?
你就陪我去
It seems so.
好像有这么回事吧
I see you are idle today.
我看你今天也闲着
So today?
要不就今天吧
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Why do you
你今天
buy me a hamburger today?
怎么请我吃汉堡呀
Because it's happy and relaxing
因为看你吃饭有幸福感
to watch you eating.
减压
My dad also thinks so.
我爸也这么说我
Dango
团子
Let me ask you something.
我问你个事
OK.
嗯
What do you think
你说
is the feeling when falling in love?
恋爱是一种什么感觉啊
You are in love?
你恋爱了
No.
我没有
I...
我就是
I watched TV series.
我看电视剧
Then
然后呢
I didn't quite understand
我看着有个桥段有点
a plot.
我 我没太明白
So I decided to ask you.
所以我就问问你
Oh.
哦
Watch TV series?
看电视剧是吧
All right.
好吧
I think
我觉得
falling in love means
恋爱就是
that he shines
他整个人都闪闪地发光
like the sun.
就像太阳一样
You feel like everything
感觉任何东西
is getting cute.
都变可爱了
When you think about it like this,
这么想着想着
you only have him in your eyes
不知不觉地
before you know it.
你的眼里就只有他
You keep looking at him
一直看着他
as if his whole face
仿佛他整个人的面容
is very close to you.
离你特别近
His every move
一颦一笑
and any small expression
任何细小的表情
will be firmly remembered by you.
都会被眼睛贪婪地记住
Then
然后呢
you can see him at school,
能够在学校看到他
and you will feel
你会觉得
very happy to go to school.
上学也是蛮开心的
You even pretend
甚至还会假装
to make excuses
因为有其他事情
to see him secretly
去到他
where he is.
在的地方偷偷看他
But as long as
不过 只要一面对面
you meet him face to face,
你就会特别紧张
you will be very nervous.
紧张得不得了
You think about it
思来想去
and don't know what to say,
也不知道该说什么好
so you leave.
就溜之大吉了
Although you are very happy,
虽然很开心
it is also very difficult.
但也很难熬
You wanna meet, but you are afraid.
想见面又退避三舍
You wanna talk, but you can't.
想说话又说不出口
Is that love?
那是喜欢吗
Take care.
慢走
Thank you.
谢谢啊 谢谢
Please, check out.
你好 结账
Just one?
就一个吗
Yes.
嗯
Are you two together?
两位是一起的吗
Yes.
是 是
And
是这样的
we have a discount
我们海豚公仔
on dolphin dolls.
有在做活动哦
If you buy two or more
买两个及以上
and then pay an additional 30 yuan,
外加三十块钱
we give you two
可以送两条
free dolphin pendants.
海豚挂件哦
Well.
好啊
Ah?
啊
I mean
我的意思是
it's free anyway.
这种便宜不占白不占
By the way,
哦对了 还有这个挂件
I don't need two pendants,
我一个人也用不了两条
so I'll give you one.
送你一个
So
所以说
the formation of social morality
社会道德的形成
is
是对
a normalization of standards of behavior.
行为标准的一种规范化
Do you have any ideas on this?
大家对这一点有想法吗
If a poor student
如果一个贫困生
uses a
用了一件
luxury item
比较奢侈的物品
or
或者是
spends a lot of money,
有了高消费的行为
should he be disqualified
他是不是应该被取消
from applying for the student grant?
申请助学基金的资格
Is this
这算不算
a discussion about standards?
是关于标准的讨论呢
Yes.
算
Does anyone
关于这个问题
answer her
有没有同学
this question?
来回答这位同学
I am a poor student.
我自己是一名贫困生
I also got a subsidy last year.
去年也拿了学校的补助
I think
我认为
it is wrong to judge it
用是否有高消费行为
by whether there is excessive consumption behavior.
来判定是不对的
Other students
其他同学
buy a pair of AJs every semester.
每学期买一双乔丹鞋
But I buy a pair
而我攒四年的钱
with the money I saved for four years.
买了一双
If I am disqualified
如果因为我偶尔的
because of my occasional
高消费
excessive consumption,
就被剥夺资格
I think it is unfair
我认为这对贫困生
to poor students.
是不公平的
This is a violation
这是对正常
of normal rights.
权利的一种侵害
But
可是你在
when you enjoy certain benefits,
享受某种福利的同时
you should bear relative obligations.
就应该承担相对的义务
I agree.
我同意
Because most poor students
因为大部分的贫困生
don't have excessive consumption,
是不会有高消费的
there is no problem
因此把大部分
taking this
作为一个标准
as a standard.
是没有问题的
Even if you buy a pair of AJ
即使你用四年的时间
in four years,
买了一双乔丹
there must be other poor students
也一定有其他贫困生
who need the money of this pair
需要这双鞋的钱来
to pay for tuition
支付学费
and subsidize their living.
补贴生活
The subsidy rule
补助规则
does not deprive the recipient
并没有剥夺接受者
of the right to consume freely.
自由消费的权利
When there are rules,
在有规则的情况下
I think we should
我觉得我们应该
respect the rules.
尊重规则
Aren't we debating
我们现在不就是在争论
whether it should be included
是不是应该把它纳入
in the subsidy qualification for poor students?
贫困生补助资格吗
Yes.
是
But we're now...
但是我们现在
These are not essences.
这些都不是根本
I'm not sure.
我也说不好
But fundamentally speaking,
但是这个现象的
the cause of this matter
根本上来说
is that people don't like
是人们看不惯
the students who get subsidies
拿补助的同学
to enjoy excessive consumption.
还能享受比较高的消费
They always think
总会觉得
that in this case,
既然如此
you must...
你就要怎样怎样
Since you are a poor student,
既然你是贫困生
you can't afford
那你肯定买不起
anything a little more expensive.
稍微好一点的东西才对
That's not what I mean.
我不是这个意思
It doesn't matter. I understand.
没关系的 我明白
I once
我曾经
talked about it with my friends.
和朋友聊过这件事
But it is easy to think
但是这很容易让人认为
that I criticize them for discrimination.
我在批评他们歧视
I don't think
我完全不觉得
this is discrimination at all.
这是一种歧视
I can't say exactly
具体是什么吧
what it is.
我也说不好
That's right.
没错
This is not discrimination.
这不是歧视
But this is prejudice, right?
但这是偏见对吗
Go on.
接着说
Hello
这位同学
I believe
我相信
that your friend
你那个朋友
never discriminated against you.
绝对没有歧视你
But what you just said
但你刚才所说的
may be a prejudice
可能是你连自己
that you don't
都没有意识到的
even realize.
一种偏见
You stubbornly believe
固执地认为
that poor students must not
贫困生就一定不能
buy something expensive.
买好东西
People with disabilities
残疾人
must be unhappy.
就一定不快乐
Children from divorced families
离异家庭的孩子
This prejudice
这种偏见
makes me feel as if this kind of thing
让我觉得好像这种事情
must be done like this.
就一定要这样做
If it's not,
但凡不是这样做
it must be wrong.
就一定是错的
So the essence of the matter
所以这件事情的本质
is not that the rules
不是说规则
should be changed or not,
到底应不应该改
but
而是
that prejudice makes us
偏见让我们在面临
feel a sense of discomfort
这种事情的时候
when we face such matters,
内心会有一种不舒适感
and we don't know
而不知道
what the cause of the problem really is,
问题到底出现在哪里
right?
不是吗
I think you're right.
我觉得你说得很有道理
Mu Xiaoyu
那牧小鱼同学
What do you think?
你觉得呢
I agree with half.
我同意一半
Emotionally speaking,
从感情上来说
this inherent
这种固有的
perception
标签化的认知
does exist.
确实存在
But rationally,
但是从理性上看
regardless of how people feel or
无论大家的感受如何
whether this is bias or not,
也无论这是不是偏见
there is no way to address
都没有办法解决这其中
the key point that doesn't make sense.
不合理的关键点
I just finally figured it out.
我刚刚终于想明白了
This is because the student grant
因为补助
is a way of secondary distribution
是国家
from the state
二次分配的一种方式
to enable more people
为的是让更多的人
to study without being troubled by their financial situation.
能够不被经济困扰学业
My view has always been
我的观点一直是
that excessive consumption means that the financial situation is okay.
高消费就代表有余力
In this case,
既然有余力
this subsidy should
就应该把这份补助
be given to more people in need.
让给更多有需要的人
After all,
毕竟
this is the original intention of the subsidy system,
这才是补助制度的初衷
right?
不是吗
It's good.
很好
It's wonderful.
非常的精彩
I am very interested
我对牧小鱼同学
in the last paragraph
最后的一段阐述
of Mu Xiaoyu.
很有兴趣
If the subsidy
如果把发放补助
is regarded as a distribution,
看成是一项分配
its rule is directed at individuals,
它的规则是针对个体
but its target
它的目标呢
is directed at groups.
却是针对群体
The contradiction is
而矛盾点恰恰就是
whether the constraint
不能够进行
of not being able to engage in excessive consumption
高消费这项约束
can become
到底能不能成为
one of the standards for receiving subsidies.
接受补助的标准之一
The service target
而这个标准
of this standard
的服务目标呢
happens to be all college students.
恰恰是全体大学生
You can think about it
大家可以从这个角度
from this angle
再结合个体的角度
combined with the individual angle.
来好好地思考思考
This is a policy debate.
这是政策性辩题
You all think from a wrong angle.
你们思考角度都偏了
You say to use need, root, solution, gain and loss.
你说要用需根解损
Hold on.
等 等一下
Need and what?
需什么
Need, root, solution, gain and loss.
需根解损
It is one of the most commonly used tools
就是政策辩分析中
in the analysis of the policy debate.
最常用的一个工具
It is used to analyze
分析一个政策中的
the need,
需求性
root, solution,
根属性 解决性
and gain/loss ratio in a policy.
和损益比
This policy
那这个政策就是
is whether or not high spending
是否应该将高消费
should be included in the subsidy rules for needy students.
纳入贫困生的补助规则
First of all, I think
首先需求性
there is the need.
我认为是有的
This is part of
这是完善贫困补助的
improving the subsidy system.
一部分
Really?
谁说的
Improving policies
完善政策
has never been a rigid demand.
从来都不是刚需
There is
在这个世界上
no 100% perfect policy
没有百分之百
in this world.
完美的政策
However,
但是在
within a relatively reasonable range,
相对合理的范围内
there can be detailed and perfect needs.
可以有细化完善的需求
The finer it is, the higher the entropy is.
越细化则熵越高
The rougher it is,
越粗糙呢
the more unpredictable it is.
则不可预测
So
所以啊
sometimes
有的时候就
we do bad things with good intentions.
好心办坏事了
Right.
对
There is also a problem with the root.
根属性也有问题
The solution is relatively clear.
解决性倒是相对明朗
This policy
这个政策
is quite a solution
对我们现在的争论
to our current debate.
就相当有解决性
It's not right either.
也不对
Once this mechanism is introduced,
一旦引入这种机制
how to define excessive consumption?
怎样去定义高消费
How to define
怎样去界定
the level of excessive consumption?
高消费的层级
How to divide this category?
怎样去划分这个分类
All these problems
等等的问题
will make this problem
都会使这个问题
gradually unsolvable.
逐渐变得无解
You figured it out?
想明白了
Your thinking
你这样的思考
completely answers
完全回答了
the analysis
最后一项
of gain-loss ratio.
损益比的分析啊
I estimate that the gain-loss ratio is very high.
估计啊损益比很高
No.
不是
Why?
怎么不是了
This is
我这又不是政策论
not a policy debate.
那个辩论
This is not a policy analysis.
我这又不是政策分析
I'm simply struggling with
我只是单纯地在纠结
whether he meets this requirement.
他符不符合这个规定
Ma Nan, it's all your fault.
马楠 都怪你
I just say it casually.
我就随便说一说啊
Look.
你看
The problem comes out after the analysis, right?
一分析问题出来了吧
Ah.
哎呀
Ma Nan
马楠
A friend of yours
你呢 有个朋友
quarrels with his girlfriend.
然后跟他女朋友吵架了
He feels deeply wronged.
你朋友还特别委屈
Because
因为你朋友觉得
he is more rational.
跟他女朋友讲道理
But his girlfriend
而他女朋友
is more sensual.
觉得跟他讲感情
In fact,
实际上呢
your friend and his girlfriend
你这个朋友跟他女朋友
are you and Xiaoyu, right?
就是你跟小鱼 对吧
Are you a god?
你是半仙吗你
I can tell.
搞得跟我不在场一样
So what should I do?
不是 那怎么办
It's very simple.
很简单呀
This is obviously
这很明显
an important but dangerous question
就是一个选择真理
of choosing truth or love.
还是选择爱情的送命题
Choose?
选 选择
Do you know that sentence
你知不知道那句
that has been verified
数千年来
by countless men
无数男人
for thousands of years?
用鲜血验证的那句话
Women are right
女人不管说什么
no matter what they say.
都是对的
No.
不是
I don't agree with Xiaoyu.
我不同意小鱼的观点
Can't I reason with her?
我还不能说说道理了
You think you reason with her.
你觉得你在跟她讲道理
But she thinks you don't love her.
她就觉得你不爱她
That's too unreasonable.
那也太无理取闹了吧
I...
我
Then
这样吧
let me ask you a question.
我问你个问题
Do you wanna be lonely all your life?
你想孤独终老吗
Listen to me.
是这样啊
Darwin said
达尔文说
that there were two types of men in this world.
这个世界上有两种男人
The first type of men
第一种男人
felt that women were right.
觉得女人都是对的
The second type of men didn't think so.
第二种男人不这么想
Then
然后呢
all the women
所有的女人
married the first type of men.
都嫁给了第一种男人
The second type of men became extinct.
第二种男人就灭绝了
Did Darwin say that?
达尔文这么说过吗
It doesn't matter.
这不重要
It is important that you understand
重要的是你得明白
that no matter what a woman asks,
女人不管说什么
you can only answer I agree.
你只能回答我同意
Then
那这样吧
I'll give you a training.
我给你训练一下
No matter what I say,
不管我说什么
you answer that I agree.
你都说我同意
OK.
嗯
Well.
好
The earth is square.
地球是方的
I agree.
我同意
You are a woman.
你是女的
Say it.
说
I agree.
我 我同意
Right.
对
Mu Xiaoyu is right.
牧小鱼是对的
I agree.
我同意
Louder please.
大点声
Make it clear.
把 把字说清楚
I agree.
我同意
Recite it once.
朗诵腔念一遍
One more time.
再来一遍
I agree.
我同意
Done.
成了
Tell her that tomorrow.
明天就这么跟她说
Xiaoyu
小鱼
I wanna talk to you again
我想再跟你聊聊
about Ran Da.
关于冉达的事情
No need for it.
不用聊了吧
There's nothing to talk about.
也没什么可聊的
I won't change my mind.
我也不会改变想法
I still don't think
我还是觉得
he's eligible
他没有拿到
for the grant.
补助金的资格
I agree.
我同意
You agree?
你同意
I think
我 我觉得你
everything you say is right.
说得都是对的
I agree with you.
我同意你的观点
I agree.
我同意
You disagreed before.
你之前不是不同意吗
Why do you suddenly agree?
你为什么突然同意了
I
我
think carefully about
回去仔细
every word you said.
想了你说的每一句话
Anyway, I'm just changed
总之我就是被你的想法
by your idea.
改变了
I agree with you.
我同意你的想法
Then why do I feel
那我为什么
so awkward?
觉得这么别扭呢
Are you a bit emotional?
你是不是有点情绪化
Emotional?
情绪化 我
No.
我没有啊
How dare I?
我哪敢啊
Nan Bei, you think it interesting?
南北 你有意思吗
Yes.
有意思啊
What do you mean?
什么意思啊
I mean that I don't agree.
我的意思就是我不同意
I don't agree with you.
我不同意你的观点
This is moral coercion.
你这就是道德绑架
You can disagree with me.
你不同意就不同意
So why did you say yes?
那你刚开始干嘛说同意
Because you're petty.
那还不因为你小气
You...
你
Just because I have different views
你就因为我和你的观点
from yours,
不一样
you snub me, alienate me
你就冷落我 疏远我
and deliberately target me.
你故意针对我
I'm so petty
我在你心里
in your mind,
我就是这么小心眼
right?
一人是吗
I didn't think so before.
我之前没这么觉得
I feel it now.
我现在觉得了
Ah.
哎哎哎
Why do I feel
我怎么感觉
that they are more and more like a divorced couple?
他们越来越像离婚了呢
So we are
那岂不是我们
done here.
完了
I will definitely be awarded to the man.
我肯定会判给男方
I will definitely be awarded to the woman.
我肯定是跟着女方了
We won't be able to
我们是不是以后
play together anymore.
没有办法一起玩耍了
It's hard for us to even meet.
连见面都难
Dandan
蛋蛋
Dango
团子
Take care.
保重
You've been angry for so long.
你们都闹这么久了
It's time for you to make up.
该和好了
So what?
切
No need.
别了吧
I'm so petty.
我这个人小心眼得很
I don't wanna make up with him.
我才不要和好呢
I'm so boring.
我这人无聊得很
I don't make up either.
我也不和好
Connected.
接通了 接通了
Hello.
教练好
Come here.
来来来
Hello everyone.
大家好
Hello.
教练
You've seen
我们前两场比赛
our first two competitions.
你看过了
Please assign us
给我们布置一下
the next task.
接下来的任务吧
Well.
好
I've seen
我看了你们
your first few competitions.
前几场的比赛
You are generally good.
总体不错
But you have many flaws in details.
细节上瑕疵众多
Your skills are maturing.
技巧日渐成熟
But your content is slightly insufficient.
内容略显不足
You have a unique style.
风格独树一帜
But that means no style.
那等于没有风格
Hello.
老教练
Can you not pause
你能不能说话
when you talk?
别大喘气
I'm just kidding.
我是逗逗你们
Let me ask you.
我问你们
You have won several competitions recently.
你们最近赢了几场比赛
Do you think
你们自己觉得
these are knockout blows?
赢得漂亮吗
Coach
教练
These victories
我们这几场
are a little bit...
确实赢得有点
It doesn't matter.
没有关系
Just tell me
我问你们
how can we
一场辩论
win thoroughly in a debate?
怎么才能赢得精彩
Xiaoyu, you answer.
小鱼 你说
I think in a debate,
我觉得一场辩论
we should
得把它的辩题的
grasp...
深度
umm...
嗯
its depth
深度和层次给打
and level,
打出来
and push them ahead.
并且推进下去就是好的
We failed to grasp
我们这几场比赛
the depth and level of the debate in these competitions.
其实打得挺浮于表面的
That's right.
说对了
How to grasp
一个辩题
the level
你们要打出层次
and depth
打出深度
of a debate?
怎么才能做到
You should learn to
你们要学会
walk into the situation
走入到辩题所辩论的
under debate.
那个情景中去
You should dig out the essence of the problem
从真实的现实层面
from the level of the reality.
挖掘问题的本质
For example,
比方说
the last debate
上一场辩论
was the significance of
共享经济
sharing economy to social development.
对社会发展的意义
From beginning to end,
从头到尾
the other side was saying that the sharing economy
对方都在说共享经济
can let the public participate,
可以让全民参与
let the public share mutual benefit,
大众共享互利
save resources
节省资源
and promote social prosperity.
促进社会繁荣和链接
Is this really the case?
真是这样吗
Although you used your skills
虽然你们利用技巧
to refute them,
反驳了他们
you never completely
却一直没有彻底
rejected this argument.
打垮这个论点
But if
但是如果
you really investigate
你们真的去了解
and talk to some people
去找几个做单车
engaged in bicycle industry and portable charger industry,
做充电宝的人谈一谈
you will know
你们就会知道
that the so-called sharing economy
现在的所谓共享经济
is essentially Internet leasing.
本质上是互联网租赁
Those are just superficial.
那些只是表面
Its business logic
而它的商业逻辑
is the reality.
才是现实啊
In the future, you should go out
以后分析辩题
and see more
要多出去走走
when you analyze the debate.
看一看
Understand?
明白吗
Xiaoyu
小鱼
The review panel
明天
is closing tomorrow.
评议小组就要截止了
OK.
嗯
Today, the old coach said
今天老教练说
that we can't just think without action.
凡事切忌空想
No matter how different
不管我们的意见
our opinions are,
如何不同
let's meet Ran Da today
今天一块去会会冉达
and then make the judgment.
再做判断吧
OK.
好
If you are a beginner,
初学者的话呢
I suggest you buy this pair.
我建议你买这双
It has a more non-slip upper.
它鞋面比较防滑
And its lining
然后它的内胆
does not rub the feet.
也不会磨脚
It has smooth bearings.
轴承光滑
It has a raised
鞋头这边有一个加高
and impact-resistant toe.
防撞的这样一个设计
It has a good
它可以有一个很好的
cushioning effect.
缓冲效果
And it has four gears that can be adjusted.
然后它有四挡可以调节
Its wheels are wear-resistant and shock-resistant.
轮子呢 耐磨 抗震
It has a removable brake.
它的刹车是可拆卸式的
If you are a beginner,
初学者的话
I suggest you buy wheels
我的建议是
with the hardness of 70
轮子买硬度七十
and the diameter of 72.
直径七十二就可以了
It's too dangerous for you
速度太快的话
if you go too fast.
太危险了
You're so professional.
这么专业呢
The pair you're wearing
你脚上这双
is not for beginners, right?
就不是入门级的吧
Right,
我这双
of course.
当然不是入门级的了
But this pair is not too good.
当然也不算太好
How much are they?
那你这双鞋多少钱
4,000 yuan.
四千
The price is so high.
这么贵呢
That's the original price.
那是正价格
I certainly can't afford it.
我当然买不起了
I've had my eye on it for over a year.
我都看上它一年多了
But the price is so high.
但是太贵了
Later,
后来我在那个
I saw a pair of 97% new ones
二手平台上面
on the second-hand platform.
看到一双九七新的
Then I asked the seller
然后来我就问那个卖家
if he could wait for me
我说能不能商量说
for another two months.
再等我两个月
At that time,
然后那时候
I worked as a summer worker
正不是暑假在打工吗
for two months
打了两个月
and then bought it.
然后就把它买下来了
Oh.
啊
So that's what it is.
原来是这样啊
In fact,
就其实吧
I think as long as you are skilled,
我觉得只要技术好啊
it doesn't matter
就鞋子稍微旧一点
if your shoes show signs of wear.
我觉得也没什么关系
Look.
你们看这块
When I turned just now,
就是轮子边上这个
the edge of the wheel
刚才转弯的时候
rubbed against the ground and passed.
擦地过去
If I hadn't lifted
要不是我右脚
my right foot early
提前抬起来
and rushed to change lanes,
赶紧换道
I would have fallen.
指不定摔哪儿去了
If the shoes were brand new,
要是全新的话
I could have just slipped a round
这一轮下来
at least five seconds ahead of time.
刚才起码得再快五秒
You're so good.
太厉害了
I gotta run.
我先走了
If you have any other questions, you can ask me.
那有事再来问我
Well.
好好好 好
It seems that he really likes this.
看来他是真的喜欢这个
Right.
是啊
Are you okay?
怎么样
Do you have any ideas yet?
有想法了吗
I agree with him.
我认同他
I also quite sympathize with him.
也挺同情他的
But
但是
I still don't think
我还是觉得
it can be agreed.
这事不能通过
It's quite good.
挺好的
You change your mind?
你改变主意了
Of course not.
我当然没有啊
You don't wanna convince me either?
你也不想说服我了
I never wanna
我从来都没有想过
convince you, okay?
要说服你好吧
I think
我是觉得
no matter what decision you make,
无论你做什么决定
you must believe
一定要相信
that you make the right one.
自己做的决定是对的
We have analyzed
我们分析过
all the possibilities,
所有的可能性
and we have visited and investigated together.
也一起走访调研过
So just judge
就根据自己的想法
according to your own ideas.
做判断就好了
I still stick to my choice.
我依然坚持自己的选择
But I also respect your idea.
但我同时尊重你的想法
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Let's make up.
我们和好吧
Actually, I thought about it.
其实我想了想
You should not be the kind of person
你应该不是那种
who quarrels with me
因为和我意见不合
because you disagree with me.
就会吵架的人
Umm.
不是
You already know
你是不是知道前几周
I broke your headphones
我把你耳机
the other week?
弄坏那件事啊
That's really not my fault.
不是 那事真不怪我
That's Dandan' fault.
要怪就怪蛋蛋
He asked me
就他非得让我
to try if the headphones
试试那个耳机
were waterproof,
能不能防水
so I tried.
我这才试的
That's really not my fault.
真不怪我
If you're unhappy...
你要是不开心
You smile.
你笑了
If you smile, it means you're no longer angry.
笑了就代表不生气啊
Go away.
走开
The fourth sign of liking a person
喜欢一个人的表现四
is that you will make some
你会在他面前
special feminine gestures
做出一些
in front of him,
特别女人的小动作
such as running your hand through your hair.
比如撩头发
All that's left is about Ran Da.
只差冉达的了
Please state clearly your stands.
大家表态吧
I still hold the same opinion as before.
我还是维持之前的意见
Me too.
我也是
And you two?
那你们俩呢
I think
我觉得
the purpose of the grant
补助金的目的
is for a better college education
是为了更好的大学教育
and the purpose of a college education
大学教育的目的
is to give each of us
是让我们每一个人
more freedom and choices.
拥有更多的自由和选择
So we can't give up eating for fear of choking.
所以不能因噎废食
I still stick to my previous point of view.
我还是坚持以前的观点
I think
我觉得
resources given to those who need them more
资源给予更需要的人
is what we really expect,
是我们真正期望的
and even is right
甚至也是申请人
what the applicants think.
自己认为正确的
There is no wrong choice.
选择是没有错误
But it is right
但是为选择付出
to pay for the choice.
也是应该的
So
所以
I also stick to my previous opinion.
我也维持之前的意见
But I have a supplementary document.
不过我有一份补充
These are some ways
这是我提议学校
I propose that the university changes the grant.
变更补助金的一些方式
We can use big data
里面包括了用大数据
to analyze
去分析
students' spending habits,
学生们的消费习惯
the number of cafeteria visits, food
食堂就餐次数 食物
and food types
和食物种类
to nominate places for subsidies.
来提名补助的名额
To prevent their misjudgment,
为了防止他们的误判
we can also
我们还可以
send text messages to these students
提前给这些学生
in advance asking for their opinions.
发短信询问他们的意见
If they say
如果他们自己表示
they
可以
don't need the subsidy,
不需要补助的话
we can
咱们也可以
respect their opinions.
尊重他们的意见
And the whole process
而且整个过程
is confidential,
都是保密的
which can
这样是为了
protect some students'
保护一些同学们
self-esteem.
的自尊心
I hope our opinions
希望我们的这些意见
can help the university.
能够帮助到学校吧
Very good.
非常好
Although every year there is a debate
虽然每年都有评议小组
on one case
因为某个案例
in a panel,
而引起争论的
you are the first
那你是第一个
to come up with ideas for improvement.
提出改进想法的人
This is done by Nan Bei with me.
是南北跟我一起弄的
Please vote.
那大家投票吧
Those who support Ran Da, please show your hands.
支持冉达的请举手
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Please help me see
你帮我看看
if this shade of lipstick
这个口红色号
will make my skin look fair.
显不显白啊
Not bad.
还行
This is very cheap.
巨便宜
Let's buy it together.
快帮我凑个单
There are so many shades.
这颜色也太多了吧
You pick one for me.
你帮我挑一个
Which one?
哪个
Are they different?
这不都一样吗
You know nothing.
你个男生审美
Go away.
一边去
Just this one.
就 就这个吧
I wanna buy eight.
我要买八个呢
Baby, you just have one mouth.
宝 你就一张嘴
Why do you buy so many?
你买那么多涂得过来吗
You see clearly.
你看清楚
This is a sample.
这是试用装
It's small.
这么小一点
I just wanna choose
我就想挑一个
a shade that suits me best.
自己最适合的颜色
I think
要我说呀
a girl is beautiful
一个女孩二十多岁
without makeup.
光鲜靓丽
So no makeup is needed.
化什么妆啊
Please cherish the time
珍惜自己
when you can be naturally beautiful,
可以自然美的时间吧
okay?
啊
He's right.
道理是这么个道理
But because the words come out of his mouth,
从他嘴里说出来
I wanna hit him.
你想揍他吗
Last week,
上个星期
our tutor talked to us
我们导师跟我们说
about choosing the major.
分专业的事了
Really?
你们导师跟你们说了
What do you wanna choose?
你怎么选
I must think about it.
我得考虑一下
Nan Bei, what do you wanna choose?
南北 你怎么选
I choose...
我选
Is that enough?
选够没
I don't choose.
我不选了
Boiling water overflows.
滚水四溢
Clear and simple.
透质无华
Even after
即便经过历史的
thousands of years,
千翻洗礼
boiled water
白开水
still has vigor and vitality.
依旧散发着勃然生机
The combination of tea and boiled water
茶叶与白开的结合
is a traditional
是中华文明以来
and Zen-filled way
一种传统
to entertain guests
而又充满禅意的
since Chinese civilization.
待客之道
We can experience sweetness in bitterness.
体味苦中回甘
We can conform to nature.
顺应万法自然
Ma Nan
学长
We agreed to train.
不是说要训练吗
Why are we doing this?
我们现在这是在干嘛
Train?
训练
I'm going to help you get rehabilitated.
不是来帮你复健的吗
I'm already well.
我早就好了
Then why do you make me tea?
那你还帮我泡茶干嘛
Hao
小好姐
Don't be angry.
别生气了
Tea, please.
喝杯茶啊
Please.
来
As a young man,
你这一个
why do you
大龄男青年
have the same hobby
怎么爱好跟
as old people?
老大爷一样
Ah.
哎呀
Let me tell you.
我跟你说吧
I have
我这把年纪啊
bad legs now,
腿不行了
so I can't play basketball
打球也打不动
or walk well.
走路咯吱吱响
Are you?
你有吗
I...
我
I'm okay.
我还好吧
So
所以说呀
this tea is for knee protection.
这个茶就是护膝盖的
If you have tea
哪天你有没有那种
for treating eyes,
治眼睛的
please give it to Nan Bei.
你赶紧给南北来两杯吧
It'll be best
最好是治青光眼 白内障
if it can treat glaucoma, cataract
外加两千度
and myopia with 20 diopters.
近视眼的那种
What happened to them?
他们两个怎么了
Nan Bei peeks at beautiful girls,
南北偷看美女
so she is jealous.
吃醋了
I...
我 我
I don't think they are beautiful.
我没有觉得她们好看
Look at yourself.
你看你那个样
You must think they are beautiful.
你还不觉得人家好看呢
Your eyes are almost glued to them.
你眼都快粘人家身上了
Oh.
哦
Why do you care so much?
你怎么那么在意
You're jealous, right?
你吃醋了吧
You talk nonsense.
谁吃你的醋
I'm afraid that you'll lower
我是怕你拉低
the aesthetics of our team.
我们队的审美
Hao
小好姐
Don't we have any plans today?
今天没有什么安排吗
You must be tired
前段时间赛程比较紧
because there were many competitions in the previous period.
大家都辛苦了
There are fewer competitions
这段时间一直到寒假前
between now and winter vacation.
赛事都比较少
So I suggest
所以我建议
you make
大家针对于
a special training plan
之前的比赛的问题
for the problems
每个人制定一套
in the previous competition,
特训计划
OK?
怎么样
That's great.
太好了
Let's get started.
那我们赶紧开始吧
Hao
小好姐
Umm...
那个
It is rare for us to relax for a few days.
咱们好不容易休息几天
Let's relax more.
缓缓呗
Don't be in such a hurry.
别那么急
What's wrong?
怎么着
This delays you to see the beauty?
挡住你去看美女的路了
All right.
好了 好了 来
Please.
喝这个
This can relieve internal heat.
败火啊
I think
我是觉得
people all like beautiful things.
爱美之心人皆有之嘛
Makeup
本身化妆
is the same as city outlook.
和市容是一个道理
These are both for beauty, right?
这都是美化工程对吧
Right.
是
So why did you say
之前也不知道谁说的
it's best for girls not to wear makeup
二十岁呢
before they are twenty?
还是以自然 靓丽为美
I wasn't
我那时候说的话
mature enough then.
还不够成熟
All right.
行了 行了
Stop arguing.
别吵了
It's not important.
就这么点小事 吵什么
Besides,
再说了
who doesn't wear makeup
咱们这个年纪
at our age...
还有哪个谁不化 化
Hao, you wear makeup?
小好姐 你化妆了
Light makeup.
淡妆
You wear makeup?
你化妆了
Why can't we see that?
你这怎么看不出来啊
She is capable.
你小好姐段位高
It's called foggy nude look,
人家叫雾面裸妆
commonly known as no makeup.
俗称啥也没化
We don't wear makeup.
我们不化
We're different.
我们不一样
We are natural beauty.
我们走自然路线
You don't understand.
这就不知道了吧
The British sociologist
英国社会学家
Mike Battoff said
麦克八组夫说过
that women who wear makeup
这个化妆的女性啊
earn more
那比不化妆的女性
than women who don't wear makeup.
挣得多
And they are more confident and beautiful.
而且更自信 更好看
And they have more suitors.
追的人也更多
Really?
是吗
Mike...
麦什么
Please say the name again.
名再说一遍来
You just make it up.
你这一看就现编的
You've grown up. I can't fool you anymore.
娃大了 骗不了了
I think
我是觉得嘛
women dress up for their beholders.
女为悦己者容
They must have their reasons
人家化个妆
for making up.
肯定也有自己的想法
You don't respect feminism
你这么说
by saying that.
有点太不女权了吧
Doesn't it matter how you feel?
自己喜欢不重要吗
If no one likes,
没有人喜欢的话
will her own beauty be gone?
自己本身的美就没了吗
If you
假如你要有一个
like a person,
喜欢的人
don't you
你不会把
dress yourself up
自己打扮得精致一点
to attract his attention?
为了吸引他的目光吗
No.
我不会
I will.
我就会
If I like a person,
我要是有喜欢的人啊
I will wear my AJ,
我就穿上我的大AJ
put my hand in my pocket,
然后插口袋
walk to the beautiful woman
走到那个美女的面前
and say to her
对她说
lady,
美女
what's up?
你好吗
Are you crazy?
你脑子让门夹了
It's getting more and more interesting.
越来越有意思了